This guy has made over $10 million
trading forex and cryptocurrency.
>> This might sound blasphemy on this
podcast and coming from me, but maybe
you use Oh, wow. Now, we have all of the
price action concept. I just saved you
watching 12 months of ICT videos. I'm
going to show you how to apply this. And
what it's going to allow you to do is
two super important things. It's one,
it's going to help you determine your
dream.
>> A verified 8 figure ICT trader. It's the
one and only trader mate. I'm going to
be covering the framework for actually
the entire strategy that I still use to
this day. The strategy that I've used
for several years now, your entry
technique, which is just this. I'm sorry
for any gurus that I've now ruined your
thing. Cuz this is how a lot of guys
teach people to trade.
>> Today, he is going to break down the
exact ICT concepts that he used to be
able to achieve that result. What you're
noticing here is ICT and other smart
money guys sometimes like to really make
some of these things seem complicated.
They really don't have to be that
complicated in practice. To make it even
better, he has simplified it all down to
make it simple, easy, and repeatable. No
matter if you're a beginner or an
advanced trader,
>> ICT always says like, I want to know
that the institutions are in this move.
It's institutionally sponsored. Really,
what does that mean? And it means that
you're getting a Welcome back everyone
to Chart Fanatics, the go-to channel for
the very best strategy and concept
breakdowns in the trading industry with
the very best traders in the world.
Talking of which, today we have our very
first 8 figure verified trader on chart
fanatics. He is an incredible crypto
trader, but this strategy is actually
universal whether you're futures, forex
or crypto. And he's the co-founder of
Breakout, the number one prop firm in
the crypto space. It's the one and only
Trader Mine.
>> How you doing, man? Excited to be here.
>> Thank you. I'm good. Well, let's get
straight into it, man. So, I'm very,
very excited. What are we going to be
breaking down here on the whiteboard and
what strategy are we looking at?
>> Awesome. So, I'm going to be covering uh
the framework for actually the entire
strategy that I still use to this day,
the strategy that I've used for several
years now. So, what we're going to do is
we're going to break down several
different kind of complex price action
concepts. I'll explain to you what they
are. Uh, and the goal here is to help
you identify high probability trading
areas. Ultimately, the goal is to be
able to increase your win rate. And I'm
going to give you a framework that
you're going to be able to easily apply
into your charts, and you're going to be
able to figure out things like trend,
market structure, points of interest,
different types of liquidity, external,
external, draws on liquidity, as well as
premium versus discount. So, if you're a
smart money trader, price action trader,
I know some of these concepts sound
familiar to you. I'm going to break them
down in a super visual, easy way that
you're going to be starting to uh that
you're going to be able to put into your
charts right away.
>> Love that. Let's get into it.
>> Where do we begin?
>> First thing that we're going to cover is
actually all of the price action
concepts um that you need to know to
understand this strategy. And then once
we understand these concepts, I'm going
to put it all together for you and the
trades you start taking going to be
higher probability. So first thing we're
going to talk about is just the three
directions in which price can actually
go. So when you are looking at a chart,
price can really only ever do three
things. Obviously an uptrend is the most
obvious one, right? So price is
consistently making higher lows, higher
highs, easy visual to see. This would be
considered bullish price action. The
inverse of this would then be of course
a downtrend. Right? Price is making
lower highs, lower lows, and this would
be considered bearish price action. So
these are the two main trends for price.
We can go ahead and wipe this away. The
last thing price can do obviously is go
sideways. So there's a lot of different
terms for sideways price action. You
could call it a consolidation. You could
call it a range. You could call it
reaccumulation or redistribution. So if
price is in an uptrend, then it goes
sideways, then it continues up. This
would be accumulation or reaccumulation.
What we're going to be focusing on here
is trending environments. So either
price making higher highs and higher
lows, an uptrend, or lower highs and
lower lows, which would be a downtrend.
So let's assume for this example that we
are in an uptrend. So price is making a
low to a high to another low to another
high. So it's consistently making higher
highs
and higher lows. So if you're a trader
and you want to get in on this trend,
what's the most optimal time to actually
enter the trade? You could enter the
trade here theoretically and if you're
willing to hold all this draw down and
you survive this draw down, you might
end up making money when it trades back
here, but in reality, the most optimal
area to get into the trade is at those
higher lows. And so what this framework
and this strategy is going to help you
do, it's going to help you find the most
likely areas for these higher lows to
occur. It's going to give you the best
riskreward. It's also going to give you
the best chance to find a high
probability setup on the lower time
frames knowing that you're in line with
that high time frame trend.
>> When you say higher time frames, is it
in regards to uh is it all subjective?
So like this could be the daily and then
lower time frame could be the hour or it
could be the weekly.
>> 100%. So this framework is what I use to
apply on my high time frame. High time
frame can be whatever you want, monthly,
daily, weekly. The key here is we want
at least two time frames.
>> Okay.
>> The high time frame that you do your
analysis on. The low time frame is where
you're actually doing your execution.
>> Do you have like uh any that you have
set out? So like if you said weekly, do
you have then the next time frame
already?
>> Yes. So what I generally do is if I'm
using the weekly for the high time
frame, my execution time frame is going
to be the daily or sometimes even the
H12 because I'm weird and I like the H12
time frame. But you got to pay for
Trading View Premium for that one. If
I'm using the daily or again the H12, my
execution time frame then becomes the
H1.
>> Okay.
>> If the H4 is my high time frame, my
execution time frame becomes the M15.
And then ultimately, I never really go
down this low, but for the scalpers out
there, you can go as low as the H1 and
even down to the M5 as your execution
time frame.
>> So, this is the time frame where we're
going to be applying the framework. This
is the time frame where you're actually
going to be looking for your setup.
Where do you enter? Where does your stop
go?
>> So that previous drawing that you just
had out, the higher highs, higher lows,
this essentially would be this section.
>> Exactly.
>> And what we're going to go into in terms
of like identifying and executing would
be this section.
>> I'm going to show you exactly where the
best place to look for this is going to
be.
>> Amazing.
>> So the next kind of concept that we need
to cover is market structure. So market
structure quite basic. Is the market
going up or down? Are we making higher
highs? Are we making higher lows? So
this is going to be the easiest thing to
see on your chart. I use just a three
candle swing system. So that means if I
have a candlestick here
and then I have another candlestick in
the middle
and then another candlestick here.
To me, this constitutes a swing high
because there's three candles with the
highest candle being in the middle and a
lower one on each side. Some people use
five candles. Some people do all sorts
of crazy stuff. I like the three candle
system. And this would of course be the
inverse for uh a swing low.
>> So, a market structure break means that
we need to see a candle close through
this high.
>> That will constitute a market structure
break. So, if we want to know if the
market is in an uptrend, I want to see
price putting in higher highs and higher
lows. So, every time we get one of these
new higher highs, this tells me that the
uptrend is continuing. So, you can mark
this on your chart as like an MSB.
Here's another one. And what we're
looking for now, of course, is okay,
we've just had an MSB. My anticipation
is even though price is pulling back,
I'm expecting this trend to continue.
That's the goal here. We want to find
the point at which this pullback ends
and the next leg of the uptrend
continues because this is going to be
where those high probability setups
form. Hey guys, I hope you're enjoying
this episode so far and don't forget we
send every single strategy breakdown
from every episode for free on
chartanatics.com. So the link for that
is in the description below. So just
make sure you click that. You just put
your email in and every single week we
will send you an up-to-date PDF strategy
breakdown for you to keep, to learn
from, to reference for free. And don't
forget, we're also launching Chart
Fanatics Live where your favorite
traders from Chart Fanatics will be live
trading every single day. I will also be
including special guests on the live
Chart fanatics edition. So, make sure
you go subscribe to that YouTube channel
right now. It's linked on the main
profile of Chart Fanatics. So, make sure
you're ready for that. Let's take a
break for a minute there, guys, cuz I
want to tell you about our preferred
prop firm here at Chart Fanatics, and it
is Apex Trader Funding. We are no
stranger to Apex. We've had Jadecap and
Trader Kane on Words of Wisdom and here
on Chart Fanatics. Now, they are well
known for having record payouts on Apex
of over $2 million a piece. Now, even if
you don't achieve a seven figure payout,
the reality of achieving a multi6figure
payouts with Apex is absolutely
achievable and an incredible opportunity
at that. And you can see that on screen
right now with all the incredible
payouts being paid out to traders around
the world, traders just like you. Now,
Apex is the biggest futures firm in the
entire industry and have paid out over
$500 million to traders across the
world. No matter the type of trader, you
can be one of them, too. Now, one of our
favorite things about Apex is that you
can get up to $6 million in funding
using the 20 accounts that you're
allowed to have and the 300K account at
that that totals $6 million. And another
thing that we love about Apex is that
there's no daily draw down. It's a
one-step evaluation and the fact that is
uncapped payouts and 90% of the profits
made are yours to keep. Now, don't
forget, regardless of the type of trader
that you are, you do not have to worry
about trading news as long as you are
following your day-to-day trading
strategy. The possibilities are
limitless at Apex Trader Funding. Now,
you can get up to 90% off, 90% off the
biggest discount in the entire industry
at Apex using the code CF and the link
in the description below. Thanks to them
and thanks to Chart Fanatics. Make sure
you get your futures funding with Apex.
Now, let's get back to the episode. Next
up, we're going to talk about the thing
that actually creates these higher highs
and higher lows. So, we're going to
stick with our um uptrend example here.
So, I call these POIs,
points of interest.
You're going to see a ton of different
conjecture. If you're an ICT guy, if
you're a smart money concept, who
invented the terms, it doesn't really
matter. They all kind of do the same
thing. So, you might call them PDAs, you
might call them supply and demand. I
drank the ICT Kool-Aid quite early on.
So, I use the ICT terminology. So, I use
order blocks, OBS, I use breaker blocks,
and then I use fair value gaps. Those
are the three points of interest that I
focus on.
>> Um, order blocks are going to be the one
that we're going to cover in this video
in specific, but what you'll actually
find is generally two or three of these
will actually always show up kind of at
the same time. There's an OB. Sometimes
there's a fair value gap after it.
There's a breaker. There might be a fair
value gap there as well. Sometimes you
have an OB and a breaker and a fair
value gap.
>> And that's the classic ICT. And then
it's like, well, which one do you pick?
We're actually going to help you with
that in this strategy because sometimes
people get a little lost in the minutia.
You don't need to know as much about
these as you actually think to get into
the trade. And really the crux of what
I'm going to share with you here is all
of this stuff, we're going to put it
together in a super easy way where by
the end of this video, you're going to
go on your chart, you'll be able to find
it yourself. So those are the main three
POIs that I work with. Think of the POI
is where I want to do business. So when
the market makes its pullback and we
have, let's say, an order block form
here, this is where you want to have
your alert on. I'm now paying attention
because in this area I'm now looking for
that potential higher low to form.
Exactly. So that's your order block. And
then the expectation here because the
trend leading into this was bullish is
that a higher low is going to form here
and we're going to continue that trend.
So, this optimal area
for the higher low is where I want to do
business because the likelihood of me
being right, me getting a trade that
works out is way higher here than
longing somewhere randomly in here or
somewhere randomly on the way up.
The next kind of concept that we want to
cover here is going to be liquidity.
Again, depending on who you follow and
what vernacular you use, there's a lot
of different kind of terms for
liquidity. I'm going to be talking about
three different things when it comes to
liquidity. First is your external range
liquidity. This is simply liquidity that
occurs outside of the trading range. So
if this is your price swing, okay, this
is your trading range, let's say from
here to here. Any liquidity that forms
outside of this range is external. Any
liquidity that forms within this range
is internal.
You can go way deep in the weeds on
different types of liquidity. For
simplicity sake, external range
liquidity is going to be swing highs and
swing lows that are outside of your
current trading range. Internal range
liquidity is just going to be a POI
within the range. So an order block,
this would be internal range liquidity.
And a external range liquidity would be
a swing high. Maybe it's over here on
the chart that price could be drawing
to.
>> That's the basics of it. Again, what
you're noticing here is ICT and other
smart money guys sometimes like to
really make some of these things seem
complicated. They really don't have to
be that complicated in practice.
The last thing about liquidity we're
going to talk about is the draw on
liquidity. So, there's this idea that
the market is drawn from liquidity to
liquidity. That's what moves the market.
Whether you believe it's an algorithm,
it's the boogeyman, it's the CIA, the
market makers, whoseever is moving it,
they're moving it from liquidity to
liquidity, draw on liquidity simply
means that okay, if price ran below a
swing low,
>> where is it next likely to go? Okay,
it's going to go over to some swing high
and it just bounces between liquidity to
liquidity. Draw on liquidity just simply
means what's the next likely area. Yeah.
So it's like essentially if this
liquidity is taken the the draw on
liquidity the most optimum is then the
next one which would be in this case
because the concept meaning that if the
liquidity is taken here and there's
nothing left it needs to then get
obviously the draw needs to go to.
>> So if I filled a bunch of longs here
where do I want to sell off those longs?
I want to sell them off way up there.
And so that's drawn liquidity. What
you're going to notice in the framework
that I use here is we're going to be
bouncing from
external range to internal, back to
external, back to internal. It's just
going to be this kind of oscillation.
Now, there going to be periods of time
where it doesn't work exactly like this,
of course. But this is really what's
happening. Price moves from one area of
liquidity to the next, back and forth.
It pingpongs. And that is all you really
need to know when it comes to liquidity.
The last concept we're going to cover
before we put it all together here is
premium versus discount. So in a range
we can bifurcate it into a half point
the 50% here. So this is the top of the
range. This is the bottom of the range.
The idea of premium versus discount very
simply is that discount exists at the
bottom of the range. Premium exists at
the top of the range. Now, if you want
to really get into the ICT fanboys
heads, you can draw a fib here and you
can mark out your 61.8,
your 78.6,
your 70.5,
the OT, the magic sweet spot that
everyone talks about, but really what
we're focused on here is discount is the
lower part of the range. Premium is the
upper part of the range.
>> If you think about this logically, what
do you want to do at a discount? Well, I
want to buy. I want to buy when things
are discounted. So that means longs
probably higher probability in the lower
part of the range. If I'm short, where
do I want to short close those shorts?
Well, I want to close them where the
buying occurs at the discount, the lower
part of the range. The inverse is of
course true for the upper part of the
range. If you want to sell something, I
want to sell it at a premium.
>> So I'm selling in the upper part of the
range. Exactly. Short here, buy there.
>> Yeah. I like to think of it as like I
want to buy cheap. I want to sell when
it's expensive. Okay,
>> now we have all of the price action
concepts. I just shaved saved you
watching 12 months of ICT videos. Okay,
>> just in this little basic bit here. So,
now that you have a grasp on these
concepts, I'm going to show you how to
apply this. And what it's going to allow
you to do is two super important things.
It's one, it's going to help you
determine your directional bias for your
trades. You're gonna see a thousand
YouTube videos with people talk about
their daily bias. And it's one of the
hardest things to figure out. It's easy
to notice a chart pattern and say,
"Okay, well, I've got a breaker here.
I'm going to long it with my stop here
and my entry here." But if the trend is
down, right, this might not work. You're
not going to get that result. So, how do
I get the one where it actually works in
my favor? That's daily or directional
bias. Where is price most likely going
to go to next? and then where's the
highest probability area that this setup
is going to occur and this framework is
going to show you exactly that. So I'm
now going to put together everything we
had just discussed. So let's again
assume we are in an uptrend. So price is
going to have a high here and then that
high is going to get broken. So now we
can draw a red line across there and
that's your market structure break and
then this high starts to form and we now
have our trading range. So you have the
swing low
and you take that all the way up to the
swing high that formed after the market
structure break. What we're now looking
for is the point of interest that led
price to create that higher high. So I
generally use order blocks or breakers
for this. Those are the most common ones
that I use. But that's going to
generally form somewhere down here. And
we'll just draw that as like a box.
So this is your order block.
>> In terms of your order block, how are
you identifying an order block?
>> So for me, it's very simply the down
move before a move that went up and
broke market structures.
>> So if we had,
>> this will be tricky to do here. So,
we're saying we're on the way down.
We've already been down, you know, a few
times. Um, and then you have your
bullish candle. Are you saying that your
order block essentially
would be like that? If this is
obviously,
>> assuming this continues to make a new
swing high, yeah, you can also combine
these.
>> Okay,
>> so there's a little bit of nuance here.
Some people like to combine candles.
Some people like to use a single candle.
The way I like to think of it is think
of it as the selling that occurred
before the buying that took out, you
know, this high. So, if that's three
down candles, you can use all three. If
you just want to use the very last down
candle, you can do that as well. What
you're going to realize is you don't
actually have to be as precise as you
think because remember this is the high
time frame. We're actually going to zoom
in.
>> Yes.
>> To look for the low time frame.
>> You want a bigger space.
>> Yeah. I the way I like to describe it is
what we're looking for here is you think
of it as like a scope with your sniper.
>> Mhm.
>> This is where we're zooming in now and
this is where I want to focus on. I
don't need to worry about anything
that's going on here, anything that's
going on here.
>> You don't need to have like a really
precise area because you're really going
to go snipe within that area.
>> People get so lost in the weeds like is
this the exact candle that's the order
block? And I'm like well actually it's
kind of like both of these. What you
said makes sense though in terms of if
this is let's say it's taken two candles
to go down and it gets broken in one.
You then take that area because the
definition well the concept of an order
block is essentially a block of orders.
>> Exactly.
>> Exactly. So we'll delete just this stuff
here and we can delete the little
sniper.
>> I like the sniper.
>> Let's take a break for a minute there
guys cuz I want to tell you about the
best CFD prop firm in the entire
industry. Funded Next. Funded Next is a
proud sponsor of Chart Fanatics and they
have been leading the CFD prop firm
industry for many years. Literally a top
three prop firm. Now, why is that? Let
me quickly just run through all the
incredible things that they do. First
off, they have challenges for every
trader. Whatever you're looking for,
they have. They have a one-step
challenge. They have two-step
challenges. And now, industryleading
instant funding. You get on demand
payouts. You get instant access to
funding. You get a no daily loss limit
and for every 10% you make on the
account it doubles your account size.
Mind-blowing. Absolutely crazy. Now let
me tell you though the trading
conditions they are the best in the
market when it comes to raw spreads and
there are no slippage. When it comes to
trading platforms they have MetaTrader
4, MetaTrader 5 and C trader as well.
Something unique to Funded Next is that
on every challenge type, you can get
once you've achieved 10% on your funded
account, up to 15% of the profits during
the challenge phase given back to you.
In addition to that, you can also get a
reward bonus equivalent to the same
amount as your subscription fee on your
first payout. And just in case that's
not enough, there's no time limit on
most challenges. News trading is
allowed. There's no imposed limits on
instruments or position sizes. They have
scaleup plans that can 10x your account
size. And something that they did first,
if you don't receive your payout within
24 hours, you will receive an additional
$1,000
compensation. Now, if that doesn't tell
you that they're for traders, I don't
know what will. Now, make sure you use
the code CF to get the best offer
available at Funded Next right now. The
link is in the description below. Make
sure you join Funded Next today. Now,
let's get back to the episode. We now
have our trading range. So, price is now
pulled back. We have our 50% line here,
>> which means a few things. We're now in a
discount here. So, what has happened so
far here? Seems like we've talked about
a lot, but really this is quite a simple
graph. This order block is the down move
that caused that market structure break.
Well, really what happened here is this
is external range liquidity that got
taken out. Price is now trading higher
and we now have a trading range. What
becomes the next draw on liquidity? It's
that point of interest back within the
trading range. So yeah, we want to look
to long here, but if we're up here and
maybe we get some sort of SFP here, our
drawn liquidity until we get down to
here is for shorts. So even though the
high time frame might be bullish, you
could theoretically look for low time
frame shorts knowing that price is
trying to draw back and mitigate this
order block and tag that internal range
liquidity. And then of course we're
looking for price to
create a higher low here within that POI
and it just tagged internal range
liquidity. What becomes the next target?
That old swing high. And then this
process repeats over and over and over
again. So I know it seems like trying to
remember order blocks, external range
liquidity, and all that stuff is
complicated, but if you can just kind of
get an idea of this framework, all you
need is one price leg. You need price to
create a new high, and then you need to
mark out the range and then you need to
find the order block. If you can do
those things, all the trades that you
take here are going to be so much higher
probability. Whenever you've had
examples where you're like, "Okay, I'm
trading and it made a pullback here. I
longed it and then it did this and why
did I get stopped out before the actual
move happened?" This is going to help
you avoid that because in here there's
going to be little bounces. There's
going to be little pullbacks. You might
think it's reversing and it might,
>> but the highest probability trade is
going to occur back at this internal
liquidity level, back at this point of
interest. And if you just focus on this,
you simplify all that other noise you're
looking at and you say, "Okay, this is
my weekly chart or this is my daily
chart." Great. Now, if this is the
daily, we're going down here on the H1
and we're now actually going to go look
for our entry.
>> Okay.
>> So, now go ahead and wipe all of that.
Just to emphasize, we are now going to
focus here.
>> Yes, we're focusing on here. So now
imagine we've taken that scope. At first
we were looking at the entire field. Now
we've zoomed in and we see the guy's
head, right? We're ready to get the the
head shot in Counterstrike or Call of
Duty.
>> So now we have this order block that
we're within, right? This is our high
time frame
>> OB. So let's call this just the the
daily order block.
>> Yep.
>> Just so we know. And price is on the on
the daily. This might even be one or two
candles. And you're like, well, how do I
get an entry? Well, in fact, you can
actually just enter on the daily. You
could literally enter right at the top
of the order block and you can put your
stop at the bottom and then you can
target that external range liquidity at
the high.
>> You can do that. However, if you want to
get a more precise entry, which we
always do, and get better riskreward and
get a tighter
setup, because sometimes these order
blocks are rather large and the stop has
to be super wide. Zooming in to now the
H1 chart, which is what we're on here.
This is where we're going to look for
that actual setup to form. This is where
your kind of dealer's choice occurs.
However you like to enter a trade now
that you're in line with the high time
frame bias because we have our daily
chart is bullish. We're in the daily
order block. We're expecting daily
continuation. Long setups that occur in
here are higher probability. They're not
all going to work. If it was that easy,
we'd be doing this on a yacht. But the
probability is a lot higher than trying
to find, oh well, this is an H1 SFP just
randomly in the middle of nowhere and
that, oh, why didn't that work out? But
then the H1 SFP that played out here
ended up being huge. This is the key,
and this is, I think, the thing that
most people miss early on in their
trading is they're looking for their
entry pattern to form without the high
time frame picture. So that initial
setup there that gives you the high time
frame picture. You have your directional
bias. You know exactly where you're
looking for the low time frame setup to
form and you know once the setup forms
in here, you're targeting a high time
frame higher high. That's all the
ingredients and you're at a discount.
All of the checklist that you might
have, all of those things are pinging.
So there's a variety of different setups
that you can take on a low time frame.
You can find a fractal of the high time
frame setup within here, right? You can
see a low, right? And then a high get
made and then a pullback into an H1
order block. Like you can see that form
within here. Maybe you use this might
sound blasphemy on this podcast and
coming from me, but maybe you use
indicators.
>> Oh wow.
>> And you might see you might see price do
something like this into this zone
>> and then the RSI is putting in a bullish
divergence.
Right? There's tons of different things.
The one that I'm going to share with you
is my most common setup and it's a
breaker. The reason I really like the
breaker entry is because it gives you
the entry and it gives you the
stop-loss.
>> So, what we're going to be looking to
form within this daily order block is
first a swing low on the hourly. And
we're not going to enter on the first
swing low and move away that we see and
assume that that's the bottom. I'm
actually looking for liquidity to be
engineered effectively here and people
to say, "Okay, well, we're bouncing. I'm
gonna long." And what do they do? They
put their stop right there.
>> Yeah.
>> I want to now see that swing low get
taken out. And then I want to see the
high that generated that swing low
>> get broken.
>> Get broken.
>> Would you say in terms of this uh would
it just be a bounce? Is it just a bounce
enough or do you want it to see uh it
break let's say a false break
essentially?
>> So there's a few different ways to look
at it. Some people use a change of state
of delivery. So it's as soon as it as
soon as it uh trades through the down
move. The more confirmation in my
opinion the better. Using the full break
of structure is going to give you worse
riskreward than using like an inverted
fair value gap. I don't want to get like
too crazy with the reaper death seal
fair value gap, but in theory
technically once that liquidity gets run
like you're going to see like some sort
of low time frame
>> FVG like do this and it's like oh I
could have entered right there.
>> Yeah.
>> But by waiting for at least in my
experience and the data that I've
collected by waiting for that
>> high it's increasing the probability
>> to get broken you're getting way more
confirmation. But in terms of this one
though, the engineered liquidity. Yeah.
Do you do you is that a bounce is enough
or do you want that to break as well
like a high which is essentially then
saying okay now
>> you know I mean it's kind of bringing in
early buyers. That's what I would
>> class. Yeah. So this I call it double
confirmation actually. So if you get
just this is your single confirmation.
If you actually get two shifts because
then effectively you've got a double
market structure break and the run.
>> More confirmation the better. And this
is to me this is like the most the
strategy so far is very mechanical.
Yeah.
>> This part is the most subjective. Yeah.
>> Because everyone has their intricacies
of how they like to enter. The reason I
like the breaker is because once you get
>> at least this right like at least the
swing lows form there and then you get
that run of it and then the structure
break you now have your breaker block
that forms right that's your entry. And
how would you define the breaker just
for the
>> So the breaker is going to be an order
block that breaks, right? That's like
the that's the entire title
>> essentially the same thing that we
marked out, but in this case rather than
looking to short from it, you're
expecting it to break because we're in
this higher time frame area.
>> Yeah. So like look at like imagine price
is pulling back here
>> and this would be a bullish order block
right here, right?
>> Yeah.
>> But then it doesn't work as a bullish
order block. ends up losing a low and
then reclaiming it. It's like a SR. Like
people will call it the funniest things,
right? Like it's kind of like, you know,
you have an overunder under over, right?
People call them over unders. Some
people call it a reclaim. Like there's a
bazillion different ways to
>> like inverted head and shoulders.
>> Yeah, inverted head and shoulders.
They're all It's all the same thing. But
yes, the breakers, right? It's
>> a bullish breaker is going to be a
failed bearish order block, right? Yeah.
>> And now we're getting real into the ICT
nerds here.
>> But the reason I like it so much as a
setup is because you have an entry and
then to me the risk is the stop run.
>> Yeah,
>> you could put your risk right below the
breaker, but at least because I'm a
crypto trader, I find that those get
tagged more. You get a lot of wicks in
crypto because it's less liquid.
>> So I find having my stop here, like if
if this low gets taken out, I'm wrong
anyways. And now you've got this setup
within your high time frame bias.
>> Are you holding this trade to the
external?
>> Ideally, you should, right? Because your
draw is way higher. But very much, but
very often, right, if you can get a
pretty decent riskreward in here. I'm
I'm 2R. I drisk.
>> So, I either take half off or I'll move
my stop to break even. Depends what I'm
like doing, how confident I am on the
setup. It also changes if I'm layering
like if I'm entering on the M15.
>> Mhm.
>> And then I used the H4, but then let's
and these are both bullish, but let's
say the the weekly is bearish. That's
slightly less high probability than if
all three were bullish. You know what I
mean?
>> Yeah.
>> But in theory, the idea here is you're
finding the exact moment that the high
time frame higher low is forming. Yeah.
>> That's what we're really looking for.
I'm looking for the exact moment that
the pullback on the on the daily ends
because on the daily this might just be
two candles,
right? I'm trying to find this exact
moment that this uptrend is resuming and
this is kind of the clue. Okay, we're no
longer going down. We've been trending
down into this level. Okay, now we've
got a change in character, a break of
structure. There's so many terms. um and
it's um
the optimal area to get into that higher
low and then absolutely you can ride
this thing to the high time frame,
higher high. So just one thing that
stands out to me potentially I love
everything so far, the layers, the
simplicity as you mentioned very early
on because we're looking at two time
frames. Uh we're looking at very clear
uh you know pointers, the the range, the
liquidity aspect, uh the structure and
then your your OB in this case. Uh and
then you have your area as we said we
zoom in for just this bit though what's
the reality would you say obviously each
case will be different but are is it a
reality where you might take a loss or
two in this area because it's giving
false signals breakouts wherever it may
be
>> absolutely I mean the the beauty of
trading right is asymmetric riskreward
like that's the number one all of I
should preface with all of my entries I
need is part of my checklist the
riskreward has to be a minimum of 2 to
one.
>> Yeah.
>> So, if I see this form, but like the
stop is, you know, really wide and I'm
saying, "Okay, well, the target it's
only going to be a one to one." That's
no longer a trade, even though it ticks
all the other boxes. I need a minimum of
two to one R. Got you.
>> And this is because you only need to
then win 33% of the time,
>> right? So if you can win one out of
three trades,
you're breaking even if each trade is
two to one. Like that make that was a
quantum leap in my trading was like you
always see 100% win rate. I have a 90%
win rate with your strategy. I'm like
dude I can't win 90% of my trades. I'm
lucky if I get half. Like dude, if you
can win half, you're going to be rich.
>> You're going to be rich. Like there's
>> the the math on on riskreward. When you
do it this way, it makes it seem so much
more attainable.
>> Yeah. Because if you can be right 40% of
the time, but it's 2 to1 RR, you are
profitable. So I I you absolutely are
going to have false positives. You're
going to have one that it takes out the
low, you enter, and it takes out the low
again.
>> Yeah.
>> But I'm willing to take multiple shots
here
>> because my strategy allows for it and
because I'm of the belief that I'm in
the most optimal area for the reversal
to happen.
>> Plus, it's not a case where just because
it took you out, you then enter straight
away. you needed to break again.
>> Yeah, exactly.
>> And still hit the markers that you
>> And these are great lessons, too, right?
Like you get stopped out and you go,
"Okay, well, what went wrong there? Did
I enter too early?" Maybe the breaker
form, the setup formed like right as it
touched the OB and you should have given
it some time to to work the level. You
got to remember this daily level might
be a
>> time. So, crypto
>> is not as in line with the New York
Open, the London session, things like
that. I have found over the recent years
and this is probably in part due to
institutions now getting in the pool
that it is starting to trade more like
New York open we always have a move in
crypto now we have you it's it's it's
actually shocking like you get the
pre-new york pump and then it fully
reverses on New York open like that's
been happening consistently for months
now and um that used to not be the case
that being said
>> because I trade on the higher time
frames so I'm trading weekly and the
daily a and then the daily and like the
H1.
>> Yes, there are times where it's like all
lined up, but I find the timing of the
setup that's more important for like low
time frame intraday traders.
>> Yeah, true.
>> Crypto it's it's nice cuz you know you
might get a trade on Sunday. You know,
when you're trying to watch the football
game and not pay attention to the
charts, all your alerts go off.
>> It's true. It never ends. No switching
off. Okay, cool. Let's go through, as
you say, the pros and cons. If you want,
I can do the cons on this side for you.
Let's take a break for a minute there,
guys, because I want to tell you about
our incredible sponsor, Tradezeller.
Tradezella is the number one trading
tool in the entire trading industry.
Tradezella allows you to become a more
profitable trader. Allows you to make
immense progress as a trader, no matter
if you're a beginner or an advanced
level trader because it makes journaling
easy. It makes journaling something that
is fun and enjoyable and something that
is interactive. So, no matter if you're
a crypto trader, no matter if you're a
futures trader, no matter if you're a
forex trader, no matter if you're a
stock trader, all you have to do is
select your broker, your platform of
choice, and connect it to Tradzella, and
it will automatically sync your trades
and pull all of that data onto the
dashboard, making journaling and finding
your edge and adapting your edge so
easy. In collaboration with Tradzella
and Chart Fanatic specifically, we are
actually getting the playbooks from the
episodes that we're filming with these
incredible verified traders and adding
them as playbooks onto Tradezella. So,
you can actually go on there and see the
rule sets already predefined. So, make
sure you check that out as well. Now,
you can actually get 10% off your
monthly subscription using CF10 on
Tradella right now. But more
importantly, I would say CF20 for 20%
off your yearly subscription with
Tradezella. The links for Tradzella are
in the description below. So, make sure
you go check them out. Use CF20. Get 20%
off your yearly subscription. Become a
better trader today. Now, let's get back
to the episode. So, the pros
almost spelled wrong. Go to school,
kids. So, the pros is it's simple,
right? Easy.
That was one of the biggest things that
not just drew me to this system that
I've slowly put together, but to price
action. I found indicators complicated,
man. It's like Ichimoku clouds, all
these different moving averages,
divergences, and stuff. I'm like, "Okay,
this is like complicated for me." So,
it's easy to understand and it's clean.
If you're OCD, your chart's always going
to look nice and pretty and you can post
on Twitter and get lots of likes because
that's almost as important as making
money. Of course. Um, second is it
combines a lot of price action concepts
that again people seem to over
complicate. Like you can find 500 videos
about order blocks, daily bias, market
structure, trends, and it's analysis by
paralysis. You're like, "Okay, do I
whose videos do I watch? Who's doing it
right? ICT said this. This guy's saying
this. This guy says ICT stole from this
guy." It's crazy. With this system, it
combines all of those things together.
>> So, OBS, ranges,
bias, all of it is combined just in the
framework of one price swing. You now
know the direction where you want to
look for your trade and where you think
it's going to happen and where you think
it's going to go after. It's super
mechanical. I think everyone early on,
they want something that is mechanical
because someone's like, "Oh, here's
where you look for your setup." I was
like, well, what's that mean?
>> You know what I mean? Like, this is like
almost so mechanical that you could code
it into a
>> 100%
>> into an algo.
>> Now, when we get into the cons, we'll
expound on this a little bit. And then
to your point at the very start of the
video, any asset, any time frame. So,
this is not cryptosp specific. I've used
this in um I've used this in FX. I've
used this in futures. I've used this
trading commodities. I've used this
trading crypto. It just works as long as
you're doing top down.
>> Yeah. As long following the system,
>> you need a minimum of two time frames.
Your high time frame is the one that
you're drawing your range on, and your
low time frame is the one where we're
looking for that setup on. Now, the
cons, just because it's simple, it
doesn't mean you don't have to work.
You still have to get into the charts
because it's very easy for me to draw it
for you on a whiteboard, show you a
hindsight example and say, "Look, it
happened perfectly." Everything is
different when you're doing it live. The
nuance,
>> it's game time, right? Shooting a
penalty kick in practice is way
different than doing it when you know
the lights are on you. You have to
require work. It requires work. You've
got to be able to recognize the pattern
live.
>> Um, and just because it's mechanical, I
think some people think it's all you
need. Mhm.
>> No system is purely mechanical.
>> Mhm.
>> There's always some discretion. There's
always some subjectivity. There's always
like there might be a setup that that
has all of the things. I just don't take
it.
>> Yep.
>> For whatever reason. Maybe I had a tummy
ache. You know what I mean? Or maybe
something else is going on. SPX is
nuking. Bitcoin's printing along. I
don't like it as much.
>> Yeah. So early on, I think a mechanical
strategy is great, but if you want to
become profitable, you need to make this
your own. I like to think of this is a
Trojan horse for price action. I'm
showing you like some very like basic
stuff and I'm kind of force feeding you
a bunch of like price action stuff that
you maybe don't want to learn and all of
a sudden you are marking out order
blocks. You understand daily bias now
without really
>> going through the ICT mentorship to
figure out what each one of those things
mean. So I feel like the mechanical
aspect really well the whole thing is
but then when it comes to the execution
over time and to do it successfully and
profitably long term that's where you
have to build that discretion that
intuition that that deeper understanding
>> and you might trade gold all the time
and you might say you know what the way
that Maine showed me to mark ranges it
actually works a little better this way
on gold
>> right so and that that's kind of the
last con last con like it's not always
going to work like That's trading.
>> Levels will get blown through.
>> Ranges will fail. POIs will get smoked.
In a super hard trending market, you
might not get that really deep discount
pullback where you want to look for the
setup. This is a super true for crypto
when it's trending hard.
>> You can't you can't be looking at the
daily and the weekly. You got to be on
the H4 to find pullbacks because on the
daily it's just a green candle, right?
So it it it it's not always going to
work in every trading environment.
>> So you have to know your Yeah, exactly.
your environment and the conditions
you're in.
>> You got to know your market and you got
to be malleable, right? That's one of
the things I think people there's
something about being robotic in
trading, but you still have to have the
ability to be malleable based on the
asset, the timing, all of that other
stuff. So some tips that I find make
this a even better system. Practice
obviously. So, the better you become at
pattern recognition, um, the you're
you're going to see this everywhere.
Every chart you're going to look at,
you're going to say, "Okay, there's my
range. There's my order block. There
might be a
>> put in the chart time, right?
>> 10,000 hours, whatever you want to call
it." If you're not putting in the chart
time, back testing, forward testing,
it's not going to work for you. You got
to be able to see it form live. Um, I
think adding additional confluences.
Would you say you have to be careful
with that as well
>> with the additional confluences? Yes,
because you don't want to overdo it,
right? Especially early on like when I
tell people who are learning to trade
like Bitcoin with me, I say just look at
Bitcoin in a vacuum. It's not in a
vacuum. Like if S&P is nuking, good
chance Bitcoin is going to nuke. Even if
it slightly is going up like and they're
diverging for a period of time,
>> really they're probably going to end up
going down together. So initially start
with it in a vacuum but as you get more
comfortable yes find more confluences do
cross market analysis don't just look at
your USD what's the DXY doing?
>> Yeah
>> what are these cross pairs doing and
adding those additional confluences will
increase the hit rate
>> and adding even another time frame. So
instead of just using the daily and the
H1 and you say okay well the daily is
bullish so I'm gonna look for bullish
setups on the H1. Well, if the weekly is
also bullish, that's now an even
stronger hit rate. So now, if you're in
the bottom of a daily range and the
bottom of a weekly range and then
looking for an H1 setup, that's going to
be a way higher probability trade than
one that's only based on two time
frames.
>> Do you use by any chance off topic in a
sense, but like do you use dynamic
sizing or
>> Yes. Is this where you would look to
>> Absolutely. if I have multiple
confluences like if so I took a trade on
euro the other day
>> dollar's taking out a weekly low into a
monthly fair value gap
>> that hourly setup to me it's like this
is where you get that home run trade
that's going to give you like you know
five six sevenr uh so yes I absolutely
use dynamic sizing also dynamic sizing
is super important in crypto because
when the market is regular v
>> versus crazy v like we had a period a
couple weeks ago where over a 10day
period, Bitcoin went up and down 10%
almost every day.
>> Yeah.
>> So, if you're opening a million dollar
position, like normally, and now it's
that volatile, all of a sudden you're
offside 50K
like three hours into the session and
you're like, "What the hell happened?"
So, yes, dynamic sizing. If you have
more confidence in a setup, maybe this
is where you risk two or 3% instead of
just one.
>> Let's start up the charts. Let's see
some examples, shall we?
>> All right. So, now we're going to go
over some chart examples here. So, this
is going to be painful for some uh
Bitcoiners out there because this
literally just happened. Um, but as you
can see here, we have our range. So, in
this case, it's a bearish range, right?
We had a low and a high here,
and we broke market structure to the
downside, creating a bearish price leg.
>> Yeah.
>> First thing we do is we mark out our
range. So there's the swing high down to
the swing low.
>> Next, you mark out our PD array. So in
this case, it's a bearish order block.
Again, this is the up candle for the
move down that broke that structure
there. Took out that external range
liquidity. And now we're simply waiting
for price to pull back into that area.
And that becomes the short that you want
to take. And I actually took this short.
You can also see here I pulled the fib.
It shows that we were at discount
pricing here. So, we were in the upper
part of that trading range. Again, we
want to short in a discount.
>> Yeah.
>> So, this is our high time frame. This is
the two-day chart. So, then zooming in,
you can see here I took a little bit of
a breaker setup here. We took out a
swing high. So, this is that two-day
order block here.
Took out a swing high. We broke
structure to the downside. We came and
we retest. And this is exactly the kind
of stuff you want to see to know you're
on the right side of the trade. I want
to see like ICT always says like, okay,
I want to know that the institutions are
in this move. It's institutionally
sponsored. Really, what does that mean?
It means that you're getting a big
effing move
>> in the direction of your trade. You
don't want it to just kind of do this.
That doesn't give me confidence. I want
to see a big fair value gap form. I want
to see price move down aggressively to
let me know that yes indeed my little 30
minute setup here is working this well
because it's in line with that 2D order
block that 2D order flow all based on
that basic framework.
>> So I have another example here of that
exact trade that I actually took uh in
Discord. So, we have our market
structure break. We have our bearish
order block. And in this instance, I
just took the trade off the high time
frame. So, I didn't even
let me just make it a little more zoomed
here.
I didn't even wait for price to go in on
the low time frame. I simply just took
the trade because you can you don't have
to go in and dial in your your setup if
you think that the riskreward is good
enough as is. Let's take a break for a
minute though, guys, cuz I want to tell
you about our incredible partnership
with propfirmtrader.com.
Majority of you out there are prop firm
traders. You're using prop firms to
leverage your trading skills to be able
to get more capital and to be able to
absolutely change your life. So what's
important to be able to find the right
challenge for you with the best firms
and most of all the best prices and that
is exactly what propertrader.com does.
propformtrader.com's allows you to
compare prop firms be able to find the
best challenge suited to your trading
style and get you the exclusive best
discounts in the entire industry so that
you're paying the cheapest price
possible for your prop firm challenge.
So on propfirmtrader.com, you'll be able
to use filters to be able to do that and
find the exact challenge for you. Be
able to find your favorite prop firms.
Just look on screen right now. You can
see futures firms. You can see CFD firms
with offers up to 50% off, which is
incredible. And you can also see Alpha
Capital there with a one-step challenge
with 25% off using PFT1. And there's so
many more exclusive discounts only on
propertrader.com.
It is the go-to site for all proper
traders out there. And one thing I'm
really excited about that I personally
helped to organize was the giveaway of
giveaways. The sevenf figureure giveaway
just through purchasing your challenges
for the best price through
propfrader.com. Every single week, you
will automatically be entered into an
incredible giveaway, a collaborative
effort across all of these firms on
screen between 100 to 200k accounts over
seven figures. It means that one person
every single week who's made a purchase
through proper.com
will be getting seven figures in
challenges that could completely
revolutionize your trading journey.
Again, all you do is for any of the
firms on propertrader.com,
use the code PFT at checkout and you
will automatically be entered every
single week. The link for
propertrader.com is in the description
below. Now, let's get back to the
episode. We have our range, we have our
bearish order block, we have our point
of interest, and I literally just
entered there and I put my stop above
the swing high there at the order block.
And the result was everyone cried and we
all lost a bunch of money.
>> But you made money at the same time.
>> I made money. A lot of people lost
money. I actually even posted this one
on Twitter because I'm so generous
saying this is the exact spot where we
would have a lower high.
>> Yeah,
>> the bears have a super clear
invalidation. This is the point of
breakdown. So if we're in fact seeing a
trend shift, this is the most optimal
place for that to happen. And that's all
we're really looking to do.
>> Just talking targeting the new external
>> targeting the new low. And so you can
see the candle looked really nice.
Everyone got bullish again and that same
candle closed horrifically.
>> Mhm.
>> And uh there's your full TP. So I closed
that trade. The next example I have here
is a soul trade that I took to all-time
highs. Same idea here, right? You have
your Oops. Oh my god. You have your
swing low. Mhm.
>> You have your swing high. I'm sorry. My
lines are not very straight. And then
you have your order block. So again,
what are we looking for here?
>> The last candle before the
>> There's your market structure break. So
there's your external range taken. This
is the POI that generated that fresh
high. So if this thing is going to
continue to go in its uptrend, this is
the most optimal area for that to occur.
If I drew my range out from here, this
would be the discount of the range. And
>> would you be doing your range from from
this this the absolute low or from the
low that led to the break? So the
easiest way that I tell people to do it
initially is you want to take the swing
low
>> Mhm.
>> to the swing high. Just the most
immediate one.
>> Okay.
>> Now once you get a little bit more
nuanced with it, the trading range that
you define can can change. You could use
you could say, well actually this is
really the most meaningful swing low of
this price leg because on the monthly
chart this actually is the swing low
>> and this is the swing high on the
monthly. But for simplicity sake of the
system, I tell people to just take
>> the most immediate low. What is the
exact swing low before the most swing
high? The downside of doing this is
occasionally
>> it might come down and hit this order
block, right? Which is still within this
range.
>> Yes.
>> And then that ends up being the higher
low. But for beginners and for to be
honest with you, doing it this way, it
works plenty fine. And more often than
not,
>> I think it's a problem where everyone's
trying to be perfect all the time.
>> Yeah. Well, there's again, it's that
kind of discretion aspect. What's the
swing low that matters? Like you can't
go on YouTube, you'll find 10 different
people tell you a different way to pick
your working range.
>> Yeah.
>> Right. This is the easiest way to
explain it. So again, this one you could
have just entered as soon as it
retested, stop below target the
external.
>> Yeah.
>> In this instance, I actually zoomed in.
So you can see price I zoomed in here
and I actually took a low time frame
entry off of the sweep here, but this is
the exact same trade again. We came back
to the order block. We built up some
liquidity here.
We actually ended up building up one
more low and then it ripped and that's
what you can see in the next picture
here. And this went all the way back to
all-time high. Again, how do we know
we're in line with the high time frame
move?
>> Fair value gap was formed. massive fair
value gap formed.
>> That's true. In regards to this though,
because obviously you can trade this
with crypto, but another benefit can be
that you can use this to short-term
well, it's still trading, right? Where
you you buy spot
>> and then sell when the price has gone
higher.
>> Absolutely. And we've talked about this
before, like at the end of the day, if
you want to buy Salana spot, you could
have bought it here and you would have
made money when it traded to 300, but
this was the best time to buy it.
>> And you still need to know where that
idea is wrong. Maybe you buy that spot
here and we we do this
>> and you want to cut it.
>> Maybe you need to cut that and not round
trip it back down to $10 or wherever it
might go, right? Yeah.
>> And that's the problem I think a lot of
crypto people have with spot is they
don't think of it as a trade.
>> It's still a trade, just it's a trade on
a higher time frame if anything.
>> Um, next up, I also long Bitcoin to
all-time high using the exact same
strategy. And people are like, "Oh my
god, he caught the long before 100K."
It's like with the most basic price
action of all time. You have your
trading range, a low to a high. You have
your order block. You have price pull
back into that order block. And on in
this instance, we actually got a high
time frame sweep, which is like that's
like money in the bank in my opinion.
Like if you were to enter this here and
your stop was here. Yeah.
>> And then we got this sweep, I would add
more size and I would bring my
validation up to there.
>> Okay. But in this instance, I actually
ended up zooming in if I'm not mistaken
and I entered in on a low time frame
setup. So you can see here we came into
the order block and it was just like I
was showing you guys before. I'm saying,
okay, let's see if they generate some
liquidity. Yeah, they're creating some
lows. We took one of those lows out and
now I'm just waiting for that shift.
Right. So I ended up entering quite
aggressively because this is that H12
SFP I was talking about. Yeah. But then
here's your H1 breaker.
There's your H1 market structure break.
>> There's your invalidation. So that
entire fractal,
that's exactly what you see form right
here.
>> You see it? Yeah.
>> And it's within the high time frame
zone. It creates a fair value gap almost
immediately. That tells me that I'm very
much on the got to get the the clout
from the boys. Uh but again the fact
that you get these thin long moves that
tells you that this is like an inst I
hate saying like institutionally
sponsored momentum.
>> I'm on the right side of the trade,
right? Like anytime you get that move
where it's like okay it tags your entry
and then it gets going. Fair value gaps
are the easiest way to identify that.
Like are we seeing expansive moves to
the upside? Yeah. Then I'm on the right
trade.
>> And I think that was it. So I love that.
That's literally longing the pico low of
Bitcoin and then from here it traded to
$110,000
and we entered it using two lines and an
order block. So all those ICT guys out
there who are telling you all these
different concepts and stuff, lots of it
works, but simplicity also works at
least to begin with.
>> Yeah.
>> And then you can Okay, now I want the
unicorn setup. I want the breaker plus a
fair value gap and I want an SMT
divergence between Bitcoin and ETH at
the lows. Bitcoin made a lower low, ETH
made a higher low or something. You can
add all of that
>> to this system.
>> But the main thing you said there is if
you want
>> if you want to, but it works as is. And
if you're saying, "Hey, I'm hitting 40%.
I want to get to 45 or I want to start
hitting, you know, three or four."
>> That's refining your edge. You're
sharpening the knife. But this is, like
I said, it's a Trojan horse. Here's a
bunch of stuff to get your feet wet. You
can actually take this, start marking up
your charts, and then go ahead, go crazy
with it. Add all sorts of different make
a PDF that you'll sell for $15 to
someone with your entry technique, which
is just this. I'm sorry for any gurus
that I've now ruined your thing because
this is how a lot of guys
>> I know,
>> teach people to trade. They're like,
it's the sweep and then the structure
break. It's like, well, it's just a
breaker, but whatever you want to call
it, unicorn
>> thing, go for it. But this is it, guys.
It works. Proof's in the pudding.
>> Thank you, man. I really appreciate it,
honestly. And I know everyone at home
does as well. Drop a comment of your
biggest takeaway. Any questions you have
for Maine, drop them in the comment
below. Maybe he'll see them, maybe he
won't. We'll see. But what you should
definitely check out are the links for
Maine and Breakout in the description
below. Drop a like, hit subscribe. Other
episodes are on screen. And until next
time, it's been Char Fanatics. Take a